in today's video we're going to be
looking at a mathematical challenge for
Jehovah's Witnesses so if you know
someone that's Jehovah's Witness or if
you are a Jehovah's Witness member
yourself I want to strongly encourage
you to watch this short video it's going
to be life changing stay tuned
[Music]
hey everyone Pastor Ivor Myers here and
in today's video we are going to be
looking at a mathematical challenge for
Jehovah's Witnesses this is going to be
straight to the point so please follow
along carefully let's go ahead and begin
what we're going to be doing in this
video we're going to be looking at two
books that were written by Jehovah's
Witnesses these are their official
writings on the Book of Revelation and
the Book of Daniel and so as you can see
the first book is called Revelation it's
Grand climax at hand and the second book
is pay attention to Daniel's prophecies
so what we're going to do is we're going
to start with a prophecy that Jehovah's
Witness hold as their foundational
prophecy this prophecy is found in
Daniel chapter four and just to give a
little bit of background in this
prophecy
Nebuchadnezzar has a dream
and in this dream he sees a tree uh that
ex extends into the heavens
and then there's a holy Watcher who says
cut down this tree the trees cut down a
band is put around the tree and then in
the vision we're told that seven times
or seven years a time is equal to a year
so seven years are going to pass over
this stump
before the stump is restored
and as you read on in Daniel chapter
four you come to find out that this tree
represents Nebuchadnezzar and it is a it
is a prophecy of Nebuchadnezzar
basically going crazy for seven years
he's gonna you know live out in the in
the in the wilderness with the animals
um he's going to eat grass like The Oxen
and at the end of seven years his reason
is going to return to him so that's the
explanation
um of this prophecy given by Daniel
Daniel himself explains the prophecy now
I want you to know what uh Jehovah's
Witnesses say about this prophecy so
we're going to go ahead and read from
their source and here's what it says
the Fulfillment of other Bible
prophecies help us to see when the
Lord's day begins not just for a little
context when they're talking about the
Lord's day here they're talking about a
a
time in the Book of Revelation
in which
various time prophecies are going to
come to pass and so it goes on to say
for example Daniel described a chopping
down of rulership in the line of King
David after seven times it would be
known that the most high is ruler in the
Kingdom of men so what I want you to see
here is they are now refering the very
Vision the very prophecy we just talked
about the prophecy which states that
Nebuchadnezzar was going to
go crazy for seven years but now
Jehovah's Witnesses are saying that this
prophecy has something to do with the
line of King David being cut down and
seven years or seven times are going to
pass over the kingdom of God being cut
down or cut off from the earth until
that kingdom is restored again now the
first problem that we have is
it's not a mathematical one but it's a
problem nonetheless
the problem is how do we go from this
tree
which Daniel says represents
Nebuchadnezzar to all of a sudden now
representing the line of the king of
David
how do we do that
that's something that needs to be
answered
um you can't take a symbol that is used
to represent an enemy of God
and then turn around and make that
symbol represent the people of God
you can't do that with the same symbol
now let me just say for example like in
the Book of Daniel
Babylon is described as a lion
but Jesus Christ is also described as a
lion but it's not the same lion right
the same lion doesn't represent Babylon
and Jesus these are two different even
though it's the same symbol we're
talking about two completely different
representations not found in the same
text
so we couldn't for example look at the
lion the description of the Lion in
Daniel 7 which points to Babylon and say
in a in a sort of you know in a sort of
symbolic sense the lion also represents
the line of the tribe of Judah we're
going to keep reading on
it goes on to say the major fulfillment
of that prophecy started with the
desolating of the kingdom of Judah which
is indicated by Bible evidence to have
been completed by October 607 BC so now
they're saying that there's a major
fulfillment of this time prophecy this
mathematic given in Daniel chapter 4.
this mathematic timestamp of seven years
or if we were to take those D those
years in days
2520 days which would make a total of
seven years according to the Jewish
Reckoning where a year is 360 days not
365. so 360 times 7 would yield two
thousand five hundred and twenty and
what Jehovah's Witness say is that yes
there was a literal fulfillment of this
when Nebuchadnezzar went crazy but there
is a dual application there is a greater
time period
that is here being mentioned
pointing to the kingdom of David being
restored being cut down and then after
these seven times whatever time period
this seven times is is over the kingdom
of David is going to be set back up
again on Earth
all right are you following so far I'm
laying the foundation for you to
understand the mathematical crisis that
Jehovah's Witnesses face when it comes
to this prophecy
so what they say
is that if you start from the year that
that Jerusalem was cut down which note
how they say according to the Bible is
607 BC
now
I went ahead and went into AI chat and I
just want you to see the question that I
typed in
in the AI chat
the question is when was Jerusalem
destroyed the answer is Jerusalem has
been destroyed twice the first
destruction of Jerusalem took place in
586 BC by the Babylonians under King
nebuchadnezzar2 who destroyed the first
temple and dis and deported many Jews to
Babylon the second destruction took
place in 70 CE now
I just want you to know
that this 607 date is already wrong off
the bat
it's not Jerusalem wasn't destroyed in
607 it was destroyed in 586. so I want
you to just keep that that mathematical
point
in your mind how are you starting this
particular prophecy of seven times
whatever the seven times is how are you
starting it
in a date that is already inaccurate
that tells me that whatever math you
apply however you add this 25 20 the
seven symbolic seven year period to 607
it's already wrong because history
confirms that Babylon was not destroyed
in 607 it was destroyed in 586.
okay let's keep going let's see what
they do with this prophecy
now note the section in their Book of
Daniel which talks about this seven
times and you'll notice the title seven
times that affect us in other words this
is this seven times that we're about to
address that they're about to address is
no longer talking about what happened to
Nebuchadnezzar the seven times also
affects us down at the you know at the
end of time and watch what they say
as represented by the great tree
Nebuchadnezzar symbolize world rulership
but remember the tree
stands for rulership and sovereignty far
grander than that of babylon's King
it symbolizes the universal rain
or Universal sovereignty of Jehovah now
let me just say this I don't remember
that the book says remember but I don't
remember that and I don't know if any of
you remember that what I remember
is that the tree is symbolic of
Nebuchadnezzar being cut down
it is not symbolic of uh uh Jerusalem
ruling it is not symbolic of any of that
it's symbolic of Nebuchadnezzar being
cut down
but anyway they say it represents God's
Kingdom
notice what they go on to say before
Jerusalem's destruction by the
Babylonians the kingdom centered in that
City with David and his heirs sitting
upon Jehovah's Thrones
Jehovah's Throne representing God's
sovereignty with reference to the Earth
so now they've moved from the tree
represents not just Nebuchadnezzar being
cut down but also God's sovereignty and
then they're going to go from God's
sovereignty to Jerusalem and then
they're going to go from Jerusalem uh
from Jerusalem to Jerusalem being
destroyed in 607 BC God himself watch
this God himself had such sovereignty
chopped down and banded in 607 BC when
they used Nebuchadnezzar to destroy
Jerusalem exercise of divine sovereignty
toward the Earth by a kingdom in the
line of David was restrained for seven
times so now we gotta see what do they
do with this seven times mathematically
what are they going to end up with how
are they going to connect this seven
times
to extend to a period where a kingdom or
a movement
is going to be represented as the
kingdom of God on Earth
so let's see what they say
they say the king's times or seven years
were 360 days multiplied by seven or two
thousand five hundred and twenty days so
so far the math is correct right
2520 days but what about the major
fulfillment of this dream now remember
the major fulfillment of the dream was
exactly what Daniel told Nebuchadnezzar
is exactly what the angel said the angel
said Nebuchadnezzar you're going to lose
your mind for that's the major
fulfillment of the dream but they're
saying no no that was the minor
fulfillment there's a major fulfillment
now how we get to that major fulfillment
no one knows
but let's keep reading
this was indicated by Jesus's words
Jerusalem will be trampled or trampled
on by the Nations until the appointed
times of the nations are fulfilled so
once again I want you to see not this
tree which represents Nebuchadnezzar
being cut down is now being used to
represent the trampling of Jerusalem by
the Gentiles not the Gentile King
himself being cut down but the trampling
of Jerusalem by gentiles
we have a major problem with this tree
now being used to represent something
else that is totally foreign from the
chapter but let's keep reading because
we're not focusing on that right now
this is just as a matter of fact stuff
like by the way stuff let's keep reading
the trampling began in 607 BC when
Jerusalem was destroyed and the typical
kingdom of God ceased to function in
Judah when would the trampling end at
the times of restoration of all things
when Divine sovereignty would again be
manifested toward the Earth through
symbolic Jerusalem
the kingdom of God
so now we're looking for this so-called
establishment of the kingdom of God at
the end of this seven times so notice
what they say next
if we were to count
2520 literal days from Jerusalem's
destruction in 607 BC that would bring
us only to 600 BCE a year having no
scriptural significance now they are
right it would bring us to a year that
has no scriptural significance the
reason it the reason is that you're
supposed to take the 25 20 days
literally
the the significance is Nebuchadnezzar
comes back into his right mind that's a
significance we're not to be looking for
anything else but they're saying we find
nothing of historical significance so
therefore the prophecy
wink wink
can't be literal days because nothing
happened then
watch what they go on to say
even in 537 BC when the liberated Jews
were back in Judah Jehovah's sovereignty
was not manifested on the Earth
that was so because Aruba Bell the heir
of David's Throne was not made King like
blah blah blah right let's just get to
this point since the seven times are
prophetic now here's what I need you to
focus on notice what they said since the
seven times are prophetic
we must
now I want you to highlight and Mark
that word
since the seven times are prophetic we
must apply to the 2520
the scriptural rule a day for a year
a day for a year and then they go on to
sites several verses that show that in
Bible prophecy in specific Bible
prophecy sometimes a day can equal a
year so they quoted Ezekiel four six
numbers 14 34 and by the way the day for
a year principle is a legitimate
principle when it comes to certain Bible
prophecies
let me say that again
it is a legitimate principle when it
comes to certain Bible prophecies
however
in other Bible prophecies it is not
legitimate
so for example when Jesus was prophesied
to be in the Earth for three days and
three nights we wouldn't say that he was
in the Earth for three D for three years
when a prophecy is specifically
connected to an individual in that
lifetime an individual a living person
and it says this amount of time that's
what it means this amount of time
Nebuchadnezzar is not a symbolic person
the time period cannot be symbolic but
here they for some reason take this 25
20 days and make it 25-20 years they're
applying the day for year principle
incorrectly now notice what this what
this ends up doing
what it ends up doing is if you take 607
BC and add 2 520 years you come to the
year 1914.
and this is the year that Jehovah's
Witnesses say God set up his kingdom on
Earth through the Jehovah's Witness
organization
okay
notice what they say hence this first
vision and the counsel it contains are
for the Lord's Day from when 1914 onward
so let me explain this then
what they have done is they've said okay
this prophecy brings us to 1914 1914 is
what starts the Lord's day and as a
result all the other prophecies in all
the other time prophecies will be
fulfilled from 1914 onward
and this is where there's a huge huge
huge huge problem
so let's let's just recap
three math challenges we're going to
look at two of them right now number one
explain how you get two differing values
for the 25 20.
in other words
the prophecy
states that this 2520 is allotted to
Nebuchadnezzar
how do you take a Time prophecy a
mathematical stamp
allotted to an individual
and now double that
so that there's not just one value of
literal day for day but there's a
secondary value of a year for a day for
a year
how do you do that and where else is
that done in the Bible what other time
prophecy can you point to
that has the same principle
where it is both both literal and
symbolic
that's going to be a very huge challenge
because there's no reason given in the
text
to take a number that is allotted to an
individual and say oh but in a greater
sense it also represents a day four year
so that's math challenge number one
where else can you find is there a
second witness in the Bible of any other
prophecy that is allotted to an
individual a literal time period but it
is also
symbolic
you can also apply a day for a year and
the prophecy still be true
there is no place else in the Bible that
does this
but
I need you to present I need you to see
I need you to come to that conclusion
thus the math challenge right if you're
sharing with a friend that's Jehovah's
Witness or if you are a Jehovah's
witness that are watching right now
please tell us how show your work how do
you take 25 20 literal days
and apply a second value of symbolic
days
that's number one
second math problem second math
challenge explain the starting point of
your equation you're starting in 607 BC
and it's very interesting that you said
according to Bible information according
to the Bible the date is 607 BC is that
because
perhaps there's a realization
that all historical sources
actually point to 586 587
so why ignore all the historical data
to choose a date that is going to fall
in line that is going to bring you to
the year you want it to bring you to
so show your work why 607 instead of 586
okay now let's get to the third problem
the third problem and then we're going
to wrap this up
because this is the major problem okay
the other problems are super significant
but here is the major problem
because
we see here for example hence the first
vision and the council it contains are
for the Lord's Day from 1914 onwards so
they're saying that all the other
prophecies will begin in 1914 or take
place
from 1914 onward okay so let's go ahead
and let's look at
the prophecy found in Daniel chapter 7
verse 25 another mathematic timestamp
this mathematic timestamp is the time
times and a half or the 1260 day
prophecy
so
remember
what do they do with Daniel Daniel 4
they applied the day four-year principle
and they said you must apply this
principle because this is prophecy
that's what they said let's go back and
just just so you can see that I'm not
making this up and just in case you
forgot let's go back let's go back
since the seven times are prophetic we
must
we must apply to the 2520 the scriptural
rule a day for a year let's see if they
are consistent let's see if they apply
the day for a year principle to this
prophecy in Daniel 7 25. let's read
same book Jehovah's Angels refer to the
prophetic period so note I've circled
those words prophetic period so we see
here this is prophecy so according to
the rule what should happen this should
be
1260 what years let's see what they do
Jehovah's Angels refer to a prophetic
period of a time and times and half a
Time how long is that Bible expositors
generally agree that this expression
denotes three and a half times the sum
of one time two times and half a time
since Nebuchadnezzar's seven they even
reference nebuchadnezza seven times
since nebuchadne has a seven times of
Madness amounted to seven years the
three and a half times would equal three
and a half years again the math is
correct here
but let's see what they do with this
time with this three and a half years
the prophecy is quite explicit as to
when the 1260 days would end when there
is a finishing Of The Dashing of the
power of the Holy people to pieces in
the middle of 1918 leading members of
The Watchtower bible and track Society
including its president J.F Rutherford
were convicted on false charges
sentenced to long terms of confinement
and imprisonment God's holy ones did
indeed see their work dash to Pieces
they are power broken counting back
three and a half years from mid 1918
brings us to the end of 1914. do you see
what just happened here do you see
the mathematical problem
what happened to a day four year this is
prophetic what happened to a day for a
year you're just gonna drop the rule
and all of a sudden now
this prophetic period of time times and
a half or three and a half years or 1260
days is not literal what happened to the
day four year well here's what happened
to the day four year
since the day four year would equal
1260 years a time period too long for
Jehovah's Witnesses to be around to
claim that hey our movement was part of
this fulfillment it has to be three and
a half years so that Jehovah's Witnesses
can say hey look look at what happened
three and a half years at a three and a
half year period in our Movement we were
treated really badly
thus this is evidence that the Jehovah's
Witnesses are gods they we represent
God's Kingdom on Earth
do you see the math challenge
my Jehovah's Witnesses friends do you
see the challenge
why are you inconsistent
why did you not follow the rule now let
me show you what
some Jehovah's Witnesses will say
and
I need you to listen carefully
here's what they write
the John class had to preach this
message for a definite stated time 1260
days or 42 months the same length of
time that the holy city would be
trampled underfoot this period seems to
be literal since it is expressed in two
different ways first and months and then
in days now I'm just going to mention
something here
because
if you ask a Jehovah's Witness
about the days of creation are they
literal days or symbolic days they're
going to say symbolic days now they're
going to say symbolic despite the fact
that in the Book of Genesis the days are
described in two different ways evening
and morning were the first day now that
seems pretty literal to me evening and
morning that's one way of describing the
day were the first day that's another
way of the evening and morning day two
different ways
and yet here they're saying well since
the 1260 are described in two different
ways it seems to be literal
do you see the inconsistency
but it doesn't stop there
because there's there are other time
prophecies in the Book of Daniel there's
the 1290 day time prophecy and I want
you to notice what they do with this
so the 1290 days now that's found in
Daniel chapter 11 so the 1260 is found
in Daniel 7 the 1290 is found in Daniel
12. I'm sorry I said Daniel 11 Daniel
12. you can read about it there in
Daniel 12 there's a 1290 uh 1335 those
two prophecies we're coming to
notice what it says here so the 1290
days began
in early 1919
and ran until the Autumn of 1922.
whoa wait a minute if something is a
rule like I can understand an exception
to the rule
but you've already done the exception to
the rule more than you did the rule
the rule says according to you since
this is prophetic we must apply the day
four year
but then when you get to these other
prophecies that supposedly start in 1914
you drop the day for your principle why
you drop the day for your rule why
you're now going with the exception
rather than the rule why
okay
how about
the 2300 day prophecy there's a 2300 day
prophecy found in Daniel chapter eight
what do they do with that well let's
take a look from the same book
the 2300 days constitute a prophetic
period now again y'all let's work this
out remember what did we read earlier
since this is prophetic we must apply
the day for year so so far we've seen
that they haven't done that at all not
in the 1260 not in the 1290 maybe they
might do it in the 2300 let's read the
2300 days constitute a prophetic period
hence a prophetic year of 360 days is
involved this 2300 days then would
amount to
six years
four months
and 20 days
when was this period Well in the 1930s
God's people began to experience
increasing persecution in various
countries and they go on to give a date
six years four months and 20 days later
that is a supposed fulfillment of this
prophetic time period are y'all seeing
the mathematical challenge now are you
seeing the problem let me show you what
this is our last slide
and then we're going to rephrase or
we're going to go back to just list out
our challenges so you can see they
actually have a chart in the very end of
their Daniel book
and the chart lists out the one two
three four five six prophecies found in
the Book of Daniel now one of those
prophecies the 70-week prophecy is
universally understood to be a day for a
year
right and and you're going to see on
their chart that they have it as a day
for a year correctly all the other
prophecies that are supposed to be a day
for a year which they are by the way
they apply a day for a day and the one
prophecy that is supposed to be a day
for a day because it's pointing to a
very specific individual
2520 days are going to pass over you not
2 520 years because you don't live for 2
520 years Nebuchadnezzar you're you
you're a man
you're not going to live that long so
the 2520 is literal time and the one
prophecy that's supposed to be Literal
time they take that and apply the day
for a year so that they can bring it
down to their day
and then everything else that is
supposed to be a day for a year
they're like oh yeah well those are day
for day even though they're prophetic
they're day for day so that we can say
all of these prophecies were fulfilled
in our movement
math challenge number three explain the
inconsistency with the day for a year
rule which one of these prophetic
interpretations are wrong because listen
they both can't be right
either your application to the day for a
year of the day for a year prophecy to
the tree the Daniel 4 dream of of
Nebuchadnezzar either that is correct
and if it is correct
then according to the rule that you
stated in your own book
none of these other prophecies that you
mentioned the 1260 1290 the 1335
the uh
the the 1335 the 2300
none of those are correct
and if you go with the day four day
principle
in which these prophecies are a day for
Day none of those are correct because
the way you got down to the 19 to 1914
is incorrect
there is
the mathematical challenge for Jehovah's
Witnesses
that is my prayer
that
everyone that is watching this
those of you that watch those of you
that claim to be followers of of the
Lord are seeking for truth
it is my prayer that as you attempt
to answer these mathematical problems
and see that they cannot be worked out
and still
hold your Doctrine your teachings to be
true
it is my prayer that you will follow
truth wherever it goes
may God bless you
as you attempt to solve these three
mathematical problems
foreign